let's go uh we're gonna start at
[Music]
De yeah I think so yeah okay de all
right we are still talking about the
Perfection of not getting upset okay and
uh that's what we'll be talking about
all
right so there's a special kind of
patience it's
called yeah I don't
care okay say yeah I don't care yeah
okay someone say you're the most stupid
person I ever met yeah I don't
care okay that actually the ancient
language it it says yeah I don't care
Jim means yeah I don't care you know uh
so people insult you people hurt you
people steal things from you you're like
yeah yeah I don't care okay and uh
that's what we're gonna start about
today
okay so people try to irritate you
people try to hurt you and you're like
yeah okay okay yeah okay that's
okay I would was in a
car when I was living in the Mongolia
Temple that uh place is very very poor
Community uh they are Russian
refugees from uh World War
II and uh nobody has any money and
there's
one car
mechanic uh he owns a
shop and uh he
he always fixed the car you know so my
car broke my teacher's car broke I took
the car to the
mechanic and then I said I need a ride
home so he and his assistant got in the
car and they take me home in the car
they are
saying no
yeah like he say this guy I know him
he's Buddhist he's stupid guy we can
cheat him easy we can make more money
you know then he didn't know I studied
Russian in
college uh so when I got out of the car
I
said you know and he's like what you
know so just be like that you know uh
someone say something bad to you you're
just like yeah okay that's okay thank
you okay all right Deon crter n good
then he says you should study all the
bad things going to happen to you if you
really get upset
okay those of you who are studying the
Himalaya
language du is a good sure is the
uh superlative form EST EST in English
like
worstest
teacher okay sure Duke means in in in
colloquial Himalaya Duke means bad so
duk means lousiest most lousy duk duk
tub means usually tub means skillful
means but in a spoken language it means
that's the stupidest thing you can do
okay that's the TP duure that's the
stupidest thing you can do what get
angry okay the picture
is okay you have to learn how to trick
the
AI the what is
AI no no he didn't correct
me AI is artificial
idiot okay and uh my AI is especially
uncooperative uncooperative must be
those chips right
from anyway my friend
knows uh so anyway uh in English we say
you are pedaling backwards you are
riding the bicycle backwards okay it
means you are going very fast but
there's a problem with the bicycle and
the more fast you go the more you go
backwards okay so actually in this case
the artificial idiot did a good job okay
understand okay so pedaling backwards
fast going backwards very fast anger
getting upset is the best way to
destroy all your hard work to do good
deeds for like a year okay five minutes
of anger five by the way there's anger
and there's anger okay one kind of anger
is
irritation you know please don't do that
I don't like that you know that one just
destroy like one day of karma right but
real anger like
you you know this one destroy a year of
karma okay five minutes okay and and
it's it's no exaggeration it's real okay
you destroy
one year of hard work many people come
to me gu you what I came to your
teaching for 14 years good nothing
happened I'm still the same you know I
say do you get angry sometime yes you
destroyed all the good karma of course
you didn't make any progress okay of
course you didn't get better of course
your Finance didn't get better of course
your husband's still the same irritating
after 14 years years okay it's because
you get upset when you get
upset you destroy all all your old seeds
Okay that's what we're talking about
here it's possible
for one upset
afternoon to
destroy 100,000 years of good SE okay
it's very serious okay it's very very
serious okay uh don't gets
we have to understand what a serious
problem is
anger we have to
learn to just smile okay someone hurts
you okay someone cheat you someone say
something bad to you especially
online okay million people are looking
gu what I did this gu what I did this
you know and then you have to learn to
go yeah
okay that you know I can't stop it I
can't do anything the by the way with
the troll the more you complain the more
they will write so I just ignore them
you know I figure they will die sooner
or later you know so I don't worry about
it I I don't even think about it you
know and I don't get upset okay then you
then you hurt yourself you don't hurt
them you hurt
yourself this is a very
important sentence okay
uh we don't
know in this room who is bodh sappa and
who is not we don't know okay sometimes
the very nice person is not a bodh
sappa sometimes the most irritating
person is a body saer in disguise
you can say guess I have a lot of
Buddhist saers in Disguise in my
life so we actually don't know who's a
bod sapper in this room and who's not a
bod saer okay the real bod
SAA doesn't advertise you know they
don't have this sign on their forehead
I'm bodh saer you know we don't know who
body sometimes
the there's a famous story of
nasin this is
the trickster from the Arab Arab
countries n in by the way there's a
Tibetan version
a which means I cannot tell
you Uncle male organ can I say
that all right there's a real
story uh in in in in the Middle East
they call
nasin and uh one day nasin uh he's like
a bodh SAA joke jok making bodh SAA he
like to have fun with
people so he got to know a very rich guy
and then he realized that the rich guy
is very attached to his furniture in his
house you know and it's going to hurt
this rich guy the rich guy so much love
money that he cannot give it to anybody
he he has to keep it he he will not
share so nasin made friends with him
they become
friends then the rich man said to nasin
you can come and stay at my house and we
can you know talk together have dinner
together you can sleep at my house nasin
uh go to dinner with the rich guy eat
his dinner at his house the rich guy put
him in the best
bedroom then he start a fire on the
house and he run
away nasin he's called a trickster okay
bad what do you call Naughty Boy okay so
he burned the house down he run away you
know then everybody's
like why are you burn the house down the
guy is Rich the guy like you he wants to
be your friend why you burn his house
down I want to help him he's too
attached to all his things he suffering
from his attachment to his things I'm
bod SAA I I purposely burn his house
down uh to teach him not to be so
attached you see what I mean we don't so
we don't know whose body SAA maybe if
someone really love you they will burn
your house down okay seriously okay they
do something very bad to you because
they understand you need help about you
have some attachment to something okay
it's
possible maybe most of those guys are
just [__] from the last
chapter but maybe some of them is B we
don't know we don't know who's a b okay
D you apprciate by the way I'm not
teaching you to burn down rich people
house okay don't don't go home and say G
I taught us to burn down
Rich it happens to me very frequently
okay it's very famous in the ancient
books that if a lowlevel
boder gets angry at a high level bod
serer they will
destroy 100 million years of good
karma and and that's not exaggeration by
the way there's a long
discussion in the ancient book is this
exaggeration and the conclusion is no
it's correct it's accurate if a lowle
body sa gets upset at a high level body
SAA just for 10 minutes something then
they lose 100 million years of good Seas
okay uh then many people come to me I
tried to make good seat for money I
didn't get any money what's the problem
I I think this DC system don't work and
I'm like do you get pissed off at your
husband or your wife yeah I mean once a
week something like that okay so you
should be more poor after the DCI course
than before the DCI course understand
okay all
right now if you're not a
bodh and then you get upset at a
bodh 1,000 million years okay 1,000
million years now let's say we are not
bodis sappa if we get really angry at a
bhis sappa we destroy good seeds for for
your whole life you you destroy all your
whole life good SE okay then uh then the
big question comes right
who's a b saer okay gu I believe I
believe it's in the book it's in the
it's in the greatest book on this world
you know it says if you're not a buddhis
SAA and you get upset at a buddhis
SAA basically you lose all the good
karma you ever did okay you have to
start zero again okay then the big
question is
what how do I
identify a suffer how do I know who's a
body saer because I'll be careful with
those people and I'll just get angry at
the other people you know uh I I believe
the book Gish that's the big problem we
don't know who's b sometimes they
pretend to be very irritating person or
they burn your house down or something
like that okay you you don't
know okay what did my boss say when I
asked him for a donation
he's Jewish he's Israel person you know
I said will you donate um like a large
amount of money for the the bayr he said
yes you know I said thank you but why by
the way the real conversation was with
his wife he cannot spend money without
his wife permission therefore I took
both of them out to lunch you know and I
asked for the money and then I can see
their arms under the table they're they
have this Israel thing they
going I'm like I know what you're doing
under the table you know like one say
$1,000 one say no $10,000 say $20,000 I
got them up to $50,000 I gave
dessert
they then 50 it was a at that time it
was money nowadays it's just enough to
pay your tax uh so anyway
uh and when I ask him why you give me
such a big donation he say I don't
know which religion is correct you know
maybe Jud Jewish maybe Buddhist I don't
know so it's
safer to give donation to everybody okay
understand you don't know who body saer
you don't know who B saer what's a safe
thing to do
don't get angry at
anybody okay someone hurt you you're
like
okay personally okay I'm telling you old
man's
Wisdom okay I have the
right okay uh
someone gets me angry or try to get me
angry or someone hurt me I just avoid
them that's all very simple I don't
fight with them I don't defend
myself you know I just say they're
like I'm say you're right I just have to
go to the toilet I'll be right back then
I never come back and they are still in
the room
like and I'm in the toilet I go to the
out to have a
pizza
and causing it anyway all right
TR the book where it talks about that is
umala jupa entering the middle way by
Chand Master Chand and Chu
bu okay two of the greatest books in
Buddhism they say the same thing okay if
you get angry at a Boda you destroy your
your good karma you destroy your good
seeds it's safer
to just be
cool just be cool okay son say you're
the most [__] Prince I ever met
you're like okay I'll see you tomorrow
I'll meet you on this in this exact
place tomorrow then don't come
back okay it's kind of fun maybe they
will come back they will stay there for
two hours you're are you're outside
having a nice coffee
somewhere okay just avoid them this old
man's advice okay you meet a bad person
someone tries to hurt you someone tries
to steal thing from
you just avoid them okay it's and your
life is so pleasant and you're so
productive you know today my publisher
where is
chaang jaang please stand up this is the
greatest publisher in the world I'd like
to thank you yeah
she published my book in in China she
made me a rock star in in China I was in
a taxi cab sorry Taiwan and uh I was in
a taxi cab and the driver stop at the
red light and he take out the Diamond
Cutter book from under the chair and
he's reading it at the red light then
I'm
like then the bus came really jenda bus
came next to me there's a big picture of
gessi Michael and there's my book you
know and I'm
like you know then we got to the 101
Building and I got in the elevator
20 ladies screaming J
J you know then I called jaang thank you
for being my publisher you know she she
made me a a a rock star you know so
anyway
I wanted to thank her especially and
thank you for coming
yeah I forget what I was talking about
okay uh
so
uh there's a picture you got the next
picture fr
disco yeah
so recently A lot of people came from
China to my place my small town they
visit my
Cafe it was a great day it was the only
day we ever made
money uh and they all buy everything and
then they came to my house and they you
you know my house yeah and they say oh
my God G you have the most beautiful
garden and I'm like oh yeah I work very
hard on the garden actually my wife does
all the work she only trusts me to do
one thing and to cut the old
roses uh when they get old if you cut
them two will grow so this is my
responsibility you know I take credit
for the whole garden it's similar to
these C
SCM all the publishing that Rosa does
usually I get all the credit and they do
all the work you see anyway uh in
English we have an expression nipping in
the bud nipping in the bud you cut the
rows before it opens okay and this is a
very important idea with anger okay it's
a very important idea with anger so
traditionally and by the way if you
study this book for the last 14 years
with
Grandpa you can see I stole most of the
book for DCI
courses okay if you took the DCI courses
you can find most of the stuff in this
book okay because this is the greatest
book it's unbelievable okay so probably
you will recognize here
uh the DCI course about not getting
angry okay and what they say
is uh you should watch your own
mind once you get angry once you get
100% angry once you are yelling at your
husband stupid it's too late to stop
it's too late to stop it's like trying
not to be drunk after you had six
Margaritas it's too lame okay it's too
late okay you have to stop at the
beginning okay you have to stop someone
say you want a margarita you have to say
no I don't drink you know I don't I'm
sorry I don't drink don't get started
don't start
anger is the same once anger starts it's
too late no no bodh and no Buddha can
stop anger after it started once you are
angry I don't know
just jump in the car and drive 100 miles
something it's too late you you cannot
stop anger once anger is in your mind
once anger
is pretty strong in your mind it's too
late okay you have to know the danger
signs you have to study the danger signs
okay oh oh G's heart beating
up G
breathing you know
wife is
talking then maybe I'm getting angry
okay you feel off balance okay in in
Buddhism we call you're off balance okay
and and a real
Buddhist who wants to protect their good
seeds you have to learn what it feels
like to start to get angry the first
five minutes okay after 10 minutes too
late just blow it up
scream as loud as you can it's too late
you lost your seats anyway you might as
well have some
fun
okay
okay all right so watch your heartbeat
watch your breath watch your mind if you
start to get a little you're like
somebody talk to you you know by and
then it takes a few minutes right you're
like what's this person oh they criti
ing
me then you start to build up anger okay
that's the time you can stop it later
it's too late okay after that it's too
late forget it just yell as loud as you
can you know do a do a good anger a
Buddha should do everything
well so get angry 100% okay but if you
want to save your good
karma learn to watch yourself oh I'm
starting to get upset I'm starting to
get upset okay then I don't go somewhere
just go out of the
house it doesn't take a genius to stop
anger get the hell out of the place you
know get away from the person okay you
don't have to be a
psychologist you know you don't need a
llama just get out of the house you know
I'm
sorry yeah you're right I'm a bad person
I
but uh you know I promise someone to
have coffee you know I'll see you see
you in an hour then get away from the
person okay then it's very hard to get
angry with nobody there I mean it's
possible okay all
[Music]
right one thing about angry is when you
get upset you have to understand
something
it makes everybody in the room
uncomfortable okay it's you you think
you got angry and and you want to tell
everybody how somebody hurt you okay you
can't believe what this person did to me
I'll tell you a secret old man's secret
nobody
cares okay nobody in this whole room
cares who hurt you yesterday and by the
way they don't want to know about it
okay and angry people just want to tell
you you can't believe what this guy did
to me then you're just like you know if
you're me I just check out I just start
thinking about the next book I have to
write for chaang or something you know
and I I it's
important to have a special skill which
some of my older students have special
skill when you come to my class if I
talk too much then you feel sleepy and
you want to take a nap if you're a very
experienced Dharma student you can learn
to take a nap with your eyes
open now how to tell Advanced
student as they take a nap with their
eyes open they're like every 20
seconds they can sleep with the eyes
open and they nod every 20 okay you can
do it okay and when you get upset and
you are complaining about somebody to
your friends they don't care at all
trust me and they are doing this special
meditation with
you actually they are thinking about
what they have to do
tomorrow but they are trying to listen
to who's the best person at this
Veronica my
wife she often does 2hour phone call
with people people call her it's very
strange she never gets to talk at all
for two hours you can't believe with so
many you can't believe and then you know
what happened she's
like then she's cooking or you know and
she
goes you know so actually every time you
get
upset and you want to tell other people
how upset you are and you want to tell
other people how bad this other person
is let me tell you old man's secret
nobody cares they're
just okay like that you're wasting your
time and you're wasting their time okay
and it's it's like the people who call
my it's unbelievable sometimes three
hours and she's so polite she will not
she will answer the form and I'm like
didn't she say I I couldn't cook dinner
I'm like yeah I no this you know
okay he says some people are so out of
control with their
anger cha cha is a very rare word that
means to commit suicide okay they get so
upset they get so angry they even hate
thems they even get angry at themsel and
they kill thems there are people who
have so such strong anger they will be
angry atsel also and they will kills
also you saw it my brother did that okay
it it happens okay people cannot
control and this is the best way to
collect enemies in your life okay get
angry tell other people about all the
people who hurting you and then and then
everyone will hate you
also okay because listen to be honest no
one wants to hear about it and let me
tell tell you a secret okay all of your
friends don't want to hear about your
problems okay they just want to have fun
with you they don't take you out for
coffee to listen
to to you repeat all the things your
husband said yesterday you know that's
not friendship and and that's not having
a good time with somebody that's
like
$200
$200 cancel the
bet I I'll show you you're on a bus the
person next to you make a fart
okay and then you
go okay listen when the person next to
your fart turn your head this way okay
here's the fresh air okay don't go like
oh what's that
there's a tietan word for duty means
colloquial for fart okay comes from
smoke D and then yum means to
smell okay don't smell fart twice it's a
old old
philosophy
concept okay if the person next to your
fart don't be an idiot like turn your
nose this way get some fresh air okay no
one wants to smell your fart okay no one
wants to go oh tell me again what your
husband said you know no one cares to be
honest nobody cares you're wasting their
time and you're wasting your time no one
cares about all the people who hurt you
okay nobody cares really okay they just
want to your friends want to have fun
with you they want you to talk about
something nice like the new president or
something
yeah never
[Music]
mind then some people said to shantia
look I understand I shouldn't smell the
fart I understand that you know but
everybody's
fighting you know everywhere I go
everybody's having problems you know
there's nobody to talk to okay then he
says uh you okay you got that
picture this was like come on you cut
the bottom off no it is the proper
picture the LA no yeah that one it's
it's a lady with a big piece of
leather right you remember from
yesterday it was a long time
ago okay yeah don't try to cover whole
world with
leather just put your goddamn shoe on
okay don't try to go out in Kyoto and
cover the whole Kyoto with
rubber just buy a pair of shoes it's the
same thing okay don't try to fix every
stupid person you meet it's too many
okay just put shoes on okay put your
patience on put your patience on always
put on your patience and TI then go
outside okay then no matter what kind of
people you meet you're safe you will not
lose your good karma okay protect
yourself don't go to try to find every
irritating person and fix them you don't
have time there's too many trust me
there's too many okay just protect
yourself okay just protect yourself put
your own shoes on don't go to try to fix
everybody in the world you don't have
time you will die before you finish okay
it's a waste of time okay you cannot fix
all the irritating people at your job
there's too many okay but guess I only
have three people working at my job
that's what I
said there's too many to fix all of them
okay then just pretend yourself just
learn to not get upset learn to not get
angry learn to smile you know if it's
really bad go to the toilet you know I
love the I I designed my building some
of you went there last year earlier this
year 12 stories we fit like thousands of
people in this building I designed the
toilets why I meditate in the toilet I'm
telling you a deep secret okay I there's
a SP there's many many stalls you saw in
every B do you think who designed
it okay why you meet some irritating
person in your work go to the toilet sit
down you want the secret
teaching you want the secret
teaching okay here's secret
teaching I buil those toilets with
separate stall separate doors and every
time I get upset I will go in there and
close the door I will sit on top of the
toilet without opening it you see what I
mean just so I can have some peace and
quiet so nobody can find me on the
telephone you know so I I sit down there
and now I'll tell you the secret
teaching
hey
Mike hey Buddha
Mike
understand I'm talking to myself when I
become a Buddha from the toilet without
opening the lid I sit on the top then
when I'm having a bad day I talk to
Mike who's
Mike future Buddha okay Buddha said
everybody in this room who's not a
Buddha you will become a Buddha Buddha
promise Buddha promise therefore and the
word Buddha
means knows all things the word
budda means know everything in the
universe past present and
future therefore you can talk Emily can
talk to Future Buddha Emily
anytime that she can hear
she's listening right now okay you can
talk to your future Buddha this is
secret P it's logical right if there's
Buddha if Buddha knows all things if
Buddha can see all time future past
present like like a they say like a
olive in the hand in their hand Kur
kurur like an olive in the palm of their
hand they can see the past therefore you
can talk to your future Buddha from the
toilet without
pooping okay it's very efficient
everywhere there's a toilet okay go
there talk tell your problem to your
future Buddha okay here here's Emily she
sit
down relax don't forget to close the
door then say hi future Buddha
Emily by the way they never answer I
don't know
why but today I'm having a hard day you
know I got this irritating people
they're really giving me trouble you
know please send me blessing okay you
can talk to Future Buddha that's okay we
don't know okay everyone in this room
will be a Buddha if you're not a Buddha
already therefore and that Buddha the
name means sees all things you can talk
to your future self okay anytime it's
very uh cool practice you want diamond
weight practice that's real diamond W
practice okay talk to them I'm having
trouble today what my husband today is
being oh man you don't know Gibson on a
bad day oh you know and I'm just kidding
H you can talk to your future so okay
all right
means
leather uh so don't try to cover the
whole world with leather just put on
your shoes okay there's also another if
you're studying this
language Kaa also
means a
small boat it's in English it's called a
coracle which means a small uh two
person boat like a canoe uh in tiet they
make them out of leather and they are
round and when there's floods in hassa
Valley everyone uh gets into a Kaa and
floats around for a while
okay and there's a bad joke which I will
not tell
you let's remind me something in private
okay uh
Kim when
start
huh punch budy
okay it's totally impossible that you
will ever be able
to beat all your enemies in this
lifetime okay you won't have time it's
not possible you cannot
uh fight with all the irritating people
you're going to meet in your life
there's too many okay it's too many you
won't have time you will die and you
will not finish okay
therefore just fight with your anger and
the rest will take care of itself got
okay don't try to beat don't try to
fight
every stupid person you meet just fix
one stupid
person okay it's a lot quicker hopefully
okay two of them and that's the example
for wearing shoes Okay fighting with one
stupid person means putting on your
shoes you cannot fix every stupid person
in the world okay cannot but you can fix
one and if you fix one the rest you
don't have to worry about them you will
not get angry you will not get upset
okay fix one put your shoes on okay you
can talk to yourself you know someone
fighting with you your friend fighting
with you your husband fighting with you
you say oh I I gota put my shoes on
they're like why do you always say that
oh it's a joke inside joke okay
all
right talk
ch ch inside joke I gotta teach you guys
okay
friend
okay um this is an interesting sentence
and it
means uh don't try to attack attack all
of your anger at the same time there's
too
many aspects it's like trying to fix
every how many pieces in a car like
30,000 pieces in a car okay don't try to
fix 30,000 pieces in your car at the
same time okay one by one one by one
okay don't try to you buy an old car
right you buy an old house the stupidest
thing to do is to try to fix the whole
thing at the same time I have a
beautiful red pickup
truck and everything fell
apart and I mean it came that way and uh
I'm just fixing pieces one by one I
didn't try to fix the whole truck at the
same time okay just take one thing and
fix it okay
uh pick pick pick things one by one
don't try to solve all the problems in
your life
at the same time because then you will
solve none of the problems in your life
okay pick them pick them one by one okay
all
right there and he gives an example we
got that picture of
Francisco
yeah in so I don't know in in the Middle
Ages in Asia there wasn't like like a
great police force or something like
that if you catch a thief in your house
you just have to beat him up the best
you can okay no that's the old system
okay nowadays you to
anyway do so the student of a great
teacher was beating a a Thief who got
into the house
okay
L the L tried to intervene means par
intervene he couldn't get that student
to stop hitting the guy so what did he
doala CH he punched the student in the
north as hard as he can maybe some of
you got this treatment from gashi
Michael I don't know he's he want to try
to get the student to stop fighting and
he talk and talk and talk and the
student so angry won't listen so the
Llama punch the student in the nose this
is the ultimate
solution okay CH so sh so sh
God stop getting angry stop getting
angry you know if you're
not stop getting angry boom my teacher
did it to me once I never forgot it I
think still there's a bump on this side
it was this side I still
rememberin and then finally due to the
kindness of Boom the student remembered
his
philosophy understand
Dharma okay all right you guys are
sleepier than yesterday what happened
you went out last night in Koto
that's why we have the program in
Koto the serious student we take the
ront there's no place to go
out they have to sleep
CH
combo uh there's a lot of people
and there's couples in
relationships and they will have a big
fight and then one of them or both of
them they are very good at apologizing
you know like they get in a big fight
they break a couple plates in the house
uh my father uh we used to go to a
restaurant and then uh the waiter will
drop the plate and it will
go and my father always say and stay
out and I'm like finally I asked my
father what's that mean when someone
break the plate noisy you know like you
always say and stay out he said that's
what your mother says when she throws a
plate at me and I I close the door real
fast
understand okay stay out kind he says
here
there's a lot of people in the
world who are very good at
apologizing after they got angry you
know they're like oh honey I'm sorry you
know I last night I lost my temper he
says you already lost your good
karma it doesn't help to be a good
apologizer just shut up in the first
place okay don't don't be one of these
people who's very good at apologizing
that they got angry yesterday be one of
those people who didn't get angry
yesterday okay got it it's it's easier
to not get upset than to be this
expert uh apologizer the next day some
people are like that you know they're
very good the next day oh I'm so sorry
gu Michael I got upset you know I'm like
couldn't you just not get upset
yesterday you know then you don't have
to tell me anything okay got it try to
cut it off at the
moment and don't be one of those AP
people who apologize the next day okay
all
right this spelling not bka but dka
means difficult okay dumor car means is
at first
difficult okay but young if you loow
J what's the other form of this verb Lo
Jong here's here's L Jong used in its
real context you know if you get used to
it if you practice mentally inside you
can do it okay learn to not get
upset learn to stop the anger for it
gets strong and stop being a good
apologizer the next
day okay apologize before you get
angry then you don't lose the karma okay
got it okay learn to cut it
off the day before not the day after
okay all right good now we are very
lucky
because we reached the third
class Gish gets more and more
behind we have to finish we took 14
years G so
slow we I have to speed up okay if
Grandpa start to tell a story tell him
to shut up
okay
no okay here's if you took DCI anger
course
f 10
don't tell me which course
is no I'm
kidding why is it a bad idea to get uh
angry at people who hurt you okay no
means hurt you okay why is it a bad idea
to get angry why is it not worth it I'll
give a $100 for the Sanskrit root of
worth it here OS poor
p who said
that who is
that a
man I thought you in
tucon I was finally saving
[Music]
money I have a mantra it says I'll pay
$100 except accept the word except the
word except the word yeah which means
worthy the Sanskrit is AR and there's
some people who say comes from that okay
worthy of
prostration okay some people say no it's
not
our it's
our which means enemy D yeah okay either
one is nice
if somebody hits you on the head with a
stick don't get angry with them instead
you can do the following meditation okay
here's a meditation you can
do when people hurt you especially
physically with with something okay
you shouldn't get those of you stud D
you know this
story if someone hit you with a stick
you shouldn't get angry at the guy you
should get angry at the stick okay the
one who hurt you is the stick the guy
didn't hurt you okay the stick hurt you
you should get you should grab the stick
and say you mother you know you should
get angry at the stick okay uh that's
the one who really hurt you
then you then you can say no I I don't
want to get the stick didn't decide to
hit me the guy decide to hit me you know
the stick is hopeless helpless the stick
doesn't have Choice the stick doesn't
have Choice the stick has to do what the
guy say to do
therefore it doesn't help G to get angry
at the stick well then by that same
logic you should not get angry at the
guy because he's also out of control
he's controlled by
anger he's like the stick you see he
holding a stick don't get mad at the
stick get mad at the guy but the guy is
being held by somebody else
who he emotion he's being controlled by
his emotion he's like the stick he's
innocent the stick is innocent nobody
put a stick in the
jail okay they put the guy in the jail
because he swing the stick right no but
the anger swing the guy the anger swing
the guy you should get angry
at anger and you can start with the
anger that lives
here that's the closest one that's the
easiest one to you don't have to go
looking for someone else who has anger
okay so here we go should you get who
hurt
you the stick okay so get angry at the
stick no no the stick doesn't hit me the
guy hit me with the stick then I should
get angry at the guy yeah the guy's like
a stick his anger is swinging the the
stick yeah so you should be angry at his
anger
yeah but you have a closer
anger you got the one in your own mind
okay then why go to some other guy's
head to take care of the anger take care
of here first got it when someone hurts
you logically you should deal with your
own anger first logically
but people get angry are never logical
right I'm
sorry so just try to grab the stick and
hit the
guy
okay okay
good who's really to blame for the
stick yeah your own Bad Seed you made
the seed okay
so really you should borrow the stick
and hit
yourself right isn't it
logically right
okay by the way this lamb L PA means
whose fault is it okay it's not like the
L and Dong okay uh whose fault is it
it's your fault you made the
SE why are you getting upset when the
laws of the universe are playing out in
front in your own mind okay what you
should get upset at
gravity you know I hate gravity why I
fell
down like who says mother gravity you
know who talk like that you know who
blame gravity
you know you should blame the laws of
karma okay you should blame the laws of
karma got it okay you shouldn't blame
the guy with the
stick all right we still
have nine
minutes I don't think I can keep you
awake for 9 minutes but I I'll give it a
try next picture
Francisco yeah by the way I just saw eor
and e going
Anna we have to go to dinner okay just
remind me okay all right uh dma say sh
just for fun okay there's no
business uh say sh sha means the 400
verses it was written by Aya DEA who
traditionally is said to be a student of
Aya the G okay anybody with Arya and
their personal name should be pretty
cool okay
uh by the way sometimes in the books
word they just call it gppa some people
too lazy to say she gppa they just say
hey from the hund which means from the
okay it happens in the
world that
um up set patients will punch their
doctor I was going to do that a few
weeks ago but he moved too
fast uh it happens that upset patients
sometime your name means they go crazy
and they punch their they hurt the
doctor
sometimes what's that mean
word yeah sometimes children get upset
at their parents and actually strike
their parents okay weird things happen
improper things
happen Okay uh the parent or the doctor
if they are wise they will not get upset
at their children okay they will not get
angry at their
children
uh they will as out of compassion
they will do the best they can to treat
the patient or the child for
Insanity okay so you don't if you meet a
a child or or you're a doctor and you
have a patient who temporarily goes
crazy and hurts you you don't you don't
sit down and try to think of the best
way to hurt them right no no good parent
will say my child
hurt me therefore I'm going to try to
hurt my child you know it's it's that's
crazy okay if your child is temporarily
out of control and they hurt you then
you should try to help the child not to
get out of control you shouldn't hurt
them B okay got it temp we call in
English temporary insanity okay some
somebody somebody eats some strange
thing and they go crazy for two hours
you don't try to kill them or something
you you tie them up and you wait for the
two hours okay like that and it happens
with countries
also
uh people who hurt you are the same okay
they are
temporarily insane okay people who get
angry at you people who hurt you are out
of control they are temporarily insane
it's like by accident they took some
drug or something and and and when
someone takes a
drug by accident it's weird to try to
hurt them okay it's it's weird to try to
hurt them they are temporary insane and
we're supposed to love all people like
my own children you know your daughter
eats some strange medicine by accident
and try to hurt you you're not going to
try to kill your daughter you're going
to wait until they get better and then
you're going to try to help them okay
then we're the same okay people who get
angry at you are temporarily
insane and if you're a Buddhist what
you're going to try to hurt them you
know what kind of Buddhist are you you
know oh gar he says something bad to me
I have to I have to write something on
the Internet back bad I have to hurt him
also what are you a Buddhist you say
you're a Buddhist Buddhist is like man
I'm sorry I made you pissed off can I
help you you know what can I do what can
I do to make you feel better okay that's
that's a Buddhist okay Buddhist doesn't
go try to hurt other people who hurt
them a Buddhist a real Buddhist
take more interest in the bad people and
try to help them okay
uh um I'll tell you a story okay I grew
up Christian I grew up in a good
Christian Church called Episcopal and
Church of England and uh and the reason
I love to
translate is uh one of the greatest uh
translations in the world is the prayer
book of the Church of England it's
amazing it's unbelievable many people
think Shakespeare translated it uh and
uh so there was a a bishop who who did
the who actually wrote the 19 who wrote
that prayer book translated that prayer
book and um he was a strange man because
uh he he read the Christian teaching
that said uh you should treat your
enemies better than your
friends uh you should treat your enemies
with more love than your friends okay
and he actually uh you got to look it up
his name is Crawford or something like
that it sounds like that it's not that
but it sounds like that
Bishop
something uh Church of England
Anglican book of prayer okay and uh so
there was a group of people uh that he
used to help them he used to help them
to buy house or he helped them to get a
horse or or like that and then uh their
friends asked them how you got the
bishop to pay for your house how you got
the bishop to to buy you a horse they
said easy with
him uh just become his
enemy purposely become his enemy you
know and you're like what yeah why he
believes what Jesus
said what did Jesus said love your
enemies you know so this Bion if he's
ass sure that you hate him he will buy
your house or he will buy your horse
or he'll take care of you you see what I
mean and and that's what a Buddhist
that's what's a Buddhist that's a real
Buddhist okay those people who hurt you
you should take
special interest to be nice to them take
care of them okay those people who hurt
you take special interest and these guys
are so smart they hurt
him especially because they know he
believes it and and he will help them he
give them money and stuff like that it's
crazy guy what's his name come
on
Anglican what's it
Crawford
no
crar cranmer you're right cranmer Rob c
r a an m e r okay he's the one amazing
and the prayer book is amazing uh uh if
you want to see a good piece of
translation that's that's a great piece
of translation okay